<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<compendium version="5" auto_indent="NO">
    <monster>
        <name>Primus (Head and Torso)</name>
        <ac>35 (natural armor)</ac>
        <hp>3390 (90d20 + 1,530)</hp>
        <cr>50</cr>
        <trait>
            <name>Disabled</name>
            <text>
                While Primus' head and torso are disabled it cannot use innate spellcasting, make an energy blast attack, and it can only make two re-order attacks when taking the multiattack action.
            </text>
        </trait>
        <trait>
            <name>Innate Spellcasting</name>
            <text>
                Refer to Primordial Traits. In addition, Primus's spellcasting ability is Charisma (spell save DC 29, +21 to attack). When Primus casts a spell of 9th level or lower, the range and area of effect are dectupled, and any damage caused is quadrupled. Primus can innately cast the following spells, requiring no components:
            </text>
            <text>
                • At will: all cleric and enchantment spells of 9th level or lower, guidance, light, mending, produce flame, sacred flame
            </text>
            <text>
                • 10/day each: cure wounds, detect magic, inflict wounds, sanctuary
            </text>
            <text>
                • 9/day each: continual flame, silence, zone of truth
            </text>
            <text>
                • 8/day each: dispel magic, protection from energy, tongues, water walk
            </text>
            <text>
                • 7/day each: banishment, freedom of movement, locate creature
            </text>
            <text>
                • 6/day each: flame strike, scrying
            </text>
            <text>
                • 5/day each: blade barrier, heal
            </text>
            <text>
                • 4/day each: divine word, etherealness, fire storm, plane shift, symbol, teleport
            </text>
            <text>
                • 3/day each: all enchantment spells of 10th level, antimagic field, holy aura
            </text>
            <text>
                • 2/day each: all enchantment spells of 11th level, gate, mass heal
            </text>
            <text>
                • 1/day each: all enchantment spells of 12th level, order
            </text>
        </trait>
        <action>
            <name>Multiattack</name>
            <text>Primus makes four re-order attacks.</text>
        </action>
        <action>
            <name>Re-Order</name>
            <text>
                Primus selects a creature it can sense within 1000 feet of it. The creature must make a DC 37 Charisma saving throw. On a failed save, the creature takes 220 (20d20) force damage and is stunned. On a successful save the creature takes half as much damage. A stunned creature must make an additional saving throw at the end of its turn, turning into a monodrone on a failed save, or ending the effect on itself and taking 55 (10d10) force damage on a successful one.
            </text>
            <text>
                If a creature is reduced to 0 hit points by this attack it is disintegrated and rises from its own dust as a monodrone at the start of its next turn.
            </text>
        </action>
        <action>
            <name>Energy Blast (Recharge 5-6)</name>
            <text>
                Primus redirects his energy pool in a concentrated blast covering an 1,800-foot cone. Each creature in that area must make a DC 37 Dexterity saving throw, taking 130 (20d12) acid damage, 130 (20d12) cold damage, 130 (20d12) fire damage, 130 (20d12) force damage, 130 (20d12) lightning damage, 130 (20d12) thunder damage on a failed save, or half as much damage on a successfully one.
            </text>
        </action>
    </monster>
</compendium>